Guide to the Marilynne Robinson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Marilynne Robinson papers
1960-2008
YCAL MSS 609
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
14.46
(16 boxes) + 1 roll
The collection consists of writings, correspondence, other papers, and audiovisual materials. Writings include published works including Housekeeping, Connie Bronson, Mother Country, The Death of Adam, Gilead, and Home, as well as unpublished fiction and student writings. Correspondence includes family, personal, and professional correspondence, and fan mail. Notable correspondents include Robinson's agent, Ellen Levine, and her editor Pat Strachan. Both writings and correspondence include born digital components. Other papers consist of printed material, clippings, photographs, and miscellaneous papers. Audiovisual materials consist of an interview with Marilynne Robinson.
Robinson, Marilynne, 1943-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Glenn Horowitz Bookseller, Inc. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 13 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 14 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 17: Restricted until the death of Marilynne Robinson or January 1, 2050, whichever comes first. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Marilynne Robinson (1943- )
Marilynne Robinson (born November 26, 1943) is an American novelist and essayist.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of writings, correspondence, other papers, and audiovisual materials. Writings include published works including Housekeeping, Connie Bronson, Mother Country, The Death of Adam, Gilead, and Home, as well as unpublished fiction and student writings. Correspondence includes family, personal, and professional correspondence, and fan mail. Notable correspondents include Robinson's agent, Ellen Levine, and her editor Pat Strachan. Both writings and correspondence include born digital components. Other papers consist of printed material, clippings, photographs, and miscellaneous papers. Audiovisual materials consist of an interview with Marilynne Robinson.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Writings, 1960s-2008. II. Correspondence, 1970s-1990s. III. Other Papers, 1960s-2000s. IV. Audiovisual Materials.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Women authors; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Photographs; Levine, Ellen, 1939-2012; Robinson, Marilynne, 1943-; Strachan, Patricia
- October 2011 Acquisition, 1960s-2008; 14.46; (16 boxes) + 1 roll
  - Writings, 1960s-2008; Series I
    - Published works, 1980-2008 (Box 1)
      - Housekeeping, circa 1980-1982
        Scope and Contents
        Material relating to the novel, Housekeeping (1980).
        - Housekeeping - 11 - partial drafts (Box 1)
        - Novel stuff - letters, Harper's proof and printed artwork, 1981 January 5 (Box 15 (Oversize))
        - Housekeeping - 12 - drafts (Box 1)
        - Housekeeping - partial interview (Box 1)
        - Housekeeping - 1 - draft (Box 1)
        - Housekeeping - 59 - partial drafts (Box 1)
        - Housekeeping - 6 - annotated material (Box 1)
        - Housekeeping - printed material, circa 1981 (Box 1)
          Contains negatives, newspapers, and ephemera.
        - Housekeeping - Marilynne Robinson poetry (Box 1)
          Contains a poem regarding Housekeeping.
        - Housekeeping - La Maison de Noé - bound annotated material, 1981 (Box 1)
        - Housekeeping - image on Fingerbone Lake - draft, act. 1, 1982 January (Box 1)
        - Housekeeping - 13 - drafts (Box 1)
        - Housekeeping - notebook 1 (Box 1)
        - Housekeeping - notebook 2 (Box 1)
        - Housekeeping - notebooks 3 and 4 (Box 1)
        - Housekeeping - notebooks 5 and 6 (Box 1)
        - Housekeeping - notebooks 7 and 8 (Box 1)
        - Housekeeping - notebooks 9 and 10 (Box 1)
        - Housekeeping - notebooks 14-16 (Box 1)
        - Housekeeping - notebook 86 (Box 1)
      - Connie Bronson, circa 1986
        Material relating to the short story, Connie Bronson (1986).
        - Connie Bronson - notebooks 31 and 37 (Box 1)
        - Connie Bronson - 49 - pages 1-3 (Box 1)
        - Connie Bronson - 51 - excerpt (Box 1)
      - Mother Country, circa 1984-1991
        Material relating to the nonfiction book, Mother Country: Britain, the Welfare State, and Nuclear Pollution (1989).
        - Mother Country - 75 - notebook (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - 76 - notes (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - 74 - notebook (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - 70 - notebook (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - 29 - notes (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - 73 - partial manuscripts (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - miscellaneous - Quality of Ribe - photocopied articles, circa 1984-1985 (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - notebook (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - miscellaneous 2 - clippings, 1986 (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - miscellaneous 6, weeded out - clippings, 1987 (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - 7 - clippings, 1986-1987; 2 (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - clippings, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - notes, drafts, and dust jacket (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - FRED -drafts (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - FRED computer re-call - drafts (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - FRED copies - annotated drafts (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - FRED - drafts (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - Byllesby - annotated drafts (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - anecdotal evidence, see also: "handy backup" files (Box 2)
          Contains annotated drafts, clippings and correspondence.
        - Mother Country - annotated drafts and clippings, 2 (Box 2)
        - Mother Country - drafts (Box 3)
        - Mother Country - Extra copies of manuscript (Box 3)
          Contains annotated drafts.
        - Mother Country - Sellafield - annotated drafts and clippings, 1986; 2 (Box 3)
        - Mother Country - Queries - 75 - notebook (Box 3)
        - Mother Country - correspondence, 83 - lawsuit, 1989-1991 (Box 3)
        - Mother Country - Setting copy - annotated, 2 (Box 3)
        - Mother Country - Women on War - for review?, 3 (Box 3)
        - Mother Country - short galleys, 1989 February 15; 2 (Box 3)
        - Mother Country - long galleys, annotated, 1989 January 5; 2 (Box 3)
        - Mother Country - design pages for front matter (Box 3)
        - Mother Country - short galleys, 1989 February 15; 2 (Box 3)
        - Mother Country - short galleys, annotated, 1989 February 15; 2 (Box 3)
      - "The De-moralization of Society" - annotated draft (Box 4)
      - "Surrendering wilderness" - draft and notes (Box 4)
      - "Hearing Silence" - Northern Lights - annotated draft (Box 4)
      - "Heresies and Real Presences" - drafts (Box 4)
      - [Essay on Sandpoint - annotated draft (Box 4)
      - Review (Box 4)
      - "Second Errand into the Wilderness" - drafts and rejection letter, 1996 May 12 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous nonfiction 1 - drafts (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous nonfiction 2 - drafts (Box 4)
      - Published articles - photocopies (Box 4)
      - Notebook - 71 - essay draft on Calvinism (Box 4)
      - Notebook - 72 - notes on religion (Box 4)
      - Marilynne Robinson - nonfiction: drafts, fragments, notes (Box 4)
      - Research - 84 - articles and correspondence, circa 1988-2006 (Box 4)
      - The Death of Adam, circa 1998
        Material relating to the nonfiction book, The Death of Adam: Essays on Modern Thought (1998).
        - The Death of Adam - 24 - notebook, draft and notes on others' work (Box 4)
        - The Death of Adam - annotated draft (Box 4)
        - The Death of Adam, "Facing reality" (Box 4)
        - The Death of Adam, "Family" (Box 4)
        - The Death of Adam, "Tyranny of Petty Coercion" - edited draft (Box 4)
        - The Death of Adam, "Psalm 8" - draft (Box 4)
        - The Death of Adam, "Darwinism" (Box 4)
        - The Death of Adam, Marguerite de Navarre - annotated draft, 3 (Box 4)
        - More Marguerite - proofs? (Box 4)
        - "McGuffey and the Abolitionists" - 78 - draft (Box 4)
        - More McGuffey - 78 - draft (Box 4)
        - Death of Adam [?] - 80 - draft (Box 4)
      - Gilead, circa 2004
        Material relating to the novel, Gilead (2004)
        - Gilead - 88 - notebook, draft and notes (Box 4)
        - Gilead - 87 - notebook, notes and drafts (Box 4)
        - Gilead - 85 - notebook, draft and notes (Box 4)
        - Gilead - 90 - draft (Box 4)
        - Gilead - 89 - notebook, drafts (Box 5)
        - Gilead - photocopies, 2 (Box 5)
        - Gilead - photocopied draft, 5 (Box 5)
        - Gilead - annotated draft, 3 (Box 5)
        - Gilead - edited draft (Box 5)
        - Gilead - annotated draft (Box 5)
        - Gilead - draft with highlighting, 2 (Box 5)
        - Gilead - annotated draft (Box 5)
        - Gilead - edited draft (Box 5)
        - Gilead (Box 5)
        - Gilead, 2 (Box 5)
        - Gilead - annotated draft (Box 5)
        - Gilead (Box 5)
        - Gilead (Box 5)
        - Gilead (Box 5)
        - Gilead - annotated draft (Box 5)
        - Gilead - annotated draft (Box 5)
        - Gilead (Box 6)
        - Gilead - annotated draft (Box 6)
        - Gilead, 2 (Box 6)
        - Gilead (Box 6)
        - Gilead - drafts (Box 6)
        - Gilead (Box 6)
        - Gilead (Box 6)
        - Gilead - annotated draft (Box 6)
        - Gilead - photocopy of annotated setting copy (Box 6)
      - Home, circa 2007-2008
        Material relating to the novel, Home (2008)
        - Home - notebook, drafts (Box 6)
        - Home - notebook, drafts and notes (Box 6)
        - Home - notes (Box 6)
        - Home - edited draft (Box 6)
        - Home, 2 (Box 6)
        - Home - annotated draft (Box 6)
        - Home - drafts (Box 6)
        - Home - drafts (Box 6)
        - Home - annotated draft, 2 (Box 6)
        - Home (Box 7)
        - Home - annotated draft (Box 7)
        - Home - edited draft (Box 7)
        - Home - annotated draft, 2 (Box 7)
        - Robinson to Levine email, 2007 September 28 (Box 7)
        - Home - additional (Box 7)
        - Home - "Winner of the Orange Prize for Fiction" large poster (Box 16 (Roll))
    - Unpublished fiction
      Material relating to unpublished works by Marilynne Robinson.
      - Fiction - 92, 93 - drafts, fragments, notes (Box 7)
      - Fiction? - 46 - notebook (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 57 - notebook (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 53 - notebooks (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 30 - notebook (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 32 - notebook (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 17 - notebook (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 66 (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 50 (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 52 (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 68 (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 33 - notebook (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 18 - notebook (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 20 - notebook (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 25 - notebook (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 29 - notebook (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 40 - notebook (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 43 - notebook (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 82 - removed from black 2-ring binder (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 91 (Box 7)
      - Unpublished fiction - 34 - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 36 - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 38 - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 41 - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 42 - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 61 - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 21 - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 22 - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 19 - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 58 - annotated (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 26 - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 23 - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 56 - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 47 - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 48 - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 69 (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 45 - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - 53 - instructor's commentary (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - notebook (Box 8)
      - Unpublished fiction - notebook (Box 8)
    - Student writings, circa 1960s-1978
      - College writings, circa 1960s-1966
        Material concerning Marilynne Robinson's undergraduate work at Pembroke College in Brown University.
        - College - 55 - American Lit 142 notebook (Box 8)
        - College - 54 - Metcalf Hall notebook (Box 8)
        - College - notebook, 1966 (Box 8)
        - College - Faulkner paper, annotated (Box 9)
        - College - 60 - "The Heroic Couplet" (Box 9)
        - College - 63 - notebook (Box 9)
        - College - Shakespeare draft, blue 3-ring binder (Box 9)
      - Graduate school writings, circa 1960s-1978
        Material concerning Marilynne Robinson's Graduate work at the Unversity of Massachusetts and the University of Washington.
        - Dissertation/grad school - notebooks, 4 (Box 9)
        - Dissertation/grad school (Box 9)
        - Dissertation/grad school - Emerson/Poe - annotated drafts (Box 9)
        - Dissertation/grad school - notebook (Box 9)
        - Dissertation/grad school - folder (Box 9)
        - Dissertation/grad school - annotated drafts (Box 9)
        - Disseratation/grad school - 64 - with rejection letter, 1978 May 12 (Box 9)
        - Dissertation/grad school - annotated draft (Box 9)
        - Dissertation/grad school - annotated draft (Box 9)
        - Dissertation/grad school - drafts (Box 9)
        - Dissertation/grad school - annotated drafts, source material and publisher's letter, 1976 Aug. 20; 2 (Box 9)
        - Dissertation/grad school - "Shakespeare unchained", 2 (Box 10)
        - Dissertation/grad school - annotated draft (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1970s-1990s; Series II
    - Marilynne Robinson - outgoing correspondence, 1980s-1990s (Box 10)
    - "To Jorie" (Box 10)
    - "To Cort [Conley?]" (Box 10)
    - "To David" (Box 10)
    - "To Robert" (Box 10)
    - "To Virginia", circa 1981 (Box 10)
    - "To Joyce" (Box 10)
    - "To parents" (Box 10)
    - Levine, Ellen, 1980-1985 (Box 10)
    - Strachan, Pat, circa 1980 (Box 10)
    - A.P. Watt, Ltd, 1980-1985 (Box 10)
    - Bantam, 1981-1982 (Box 10)
    - Faber and Faber, 1980-1990 (Box 10)
    - Farrar, Straus and Giroux {non-Strachan), 1980-1982 (Box 10)
    - Henry Holt & Co., 1997 (Box 10)
    - Penguin, 1981 (Box 10)
    - "CVS" - curriculum vitae, 1980s (Box 10)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters / Straus Living Grant, 1982-1998 (Box 10)
    - Chane Production Co., 1989-1992 (Box 10)
    - Readings / panels / events - requests, schedules, etc., 1980s (Box 10)
    - Interviews, 1980s-1990s (Box 10)
      Separated Materials
      1 audiocasette removed to audiovisual materials.
    - Journals and anthologies, 1980s-1990s (Box 10)
    - Marilynne Robinson - Journals, etc. (Box 10)
    - University of Iowa, 1992 (Box 10)
    - Conley, Cort, 1990s; 2 (Box 10)
    - University teaching positions (non-Iowa), 1978-1980s; 2 (Box 10)
    - Hawkes, John, 1980-1981 (Box 10)
    - Lodge, David, 1995 (Box 10)
    - Moody, Rick, 1989 (Box 10)
    - Chee, Alex (Box 10)
    - Coover, Robert, 1988 (Box 10)
    - Fischer, Bruce, 1990s (Box 10)
    - Pinsky, Robert, 1992-1993 (Box 11)
    - Prose, Francine, 1997 (Box 11)
    - Richardson, Robert, 1993 (Box 11)
    - Schaire, Jeff, 1980 (Box 11)
    - Watson, Jack, 1985 (Box 11)
    - Fan mail and personal mail - miscellaneous, 1980s-1990s; 2 (Box 11)
    - Letters to Marilynne Robinson, 1981; 1990 (Box 11)
      Includes two lettters. One letter is regarding the book Housekeeping, and is dated 5 May 1980. The other is dated 20 April 1990.
  - Other papers, 1960s-2000s; Series III
    Contains printed material, photographs and various materials.
    - Press clippings, 1980s-2000s; 4 (Box 11)
    - Documents, printed material, and event materials, 1980s; 2 (Box 11)
    - Author photos and contact sheets, 1960s-2000s (Box 11)
      3 CDs removed to restricted fragile.
    - Journals and magazines, 1981-1985 (Box 11)
      Contains: The Hudson Review, Vol. XXXIV, No. 3, Autumn 1981; Brick: A Literary Journal, No. 64, 1984; Harper's, February 1985.
    - The New Yorker, 1981-1985 (Box 11)
      Contains three copies of the New York: two copies of March 23, 1981 and one copy of October 7, 1985.
    - The New Puritanism? - proof (Box 11)
    - Addition - Insomnia, 1980s (Box 11)
    - Additions 2 - Brother, circa 1985 (Box 11)
    - Additions 3 - Graham, 1982 (Box 11)
    - Additions 5 - Incoming, 1970s-1990s; 3 (Box 12)
    - Additions 6 - Pinsky (Box 12)
    - Additions 7 - Preault, 1980s; 2 (Box 12)
    - Additions 8 - Outgoing (Box 12)
    - Additions 9 - Fischer (Box 12)
    - P + S p.15: Essay on Bush/Clinton, 1992 (Box 12)
    - Annie Dillard, 2004 (Box 12)
    - Additional 11 - Fiction (Box 12)
    - Additional 12 - Fiction photocopy (Box 12)
    - Additional 13 - Book tour diaries (Box 12)
    - Additoinal 14 - Notebook (Box 12)
    - Additional 15 - Poetry (Box 12)
    - Additional 16 - Nonfiction (Box 12)
    - Additional 17 - MSS leaves (Box 12)
    - Additional 18 - Dissertation (Box 12)
    - Additional 19 - Teaching (Box 12)
    - Additional 20 - Printed matter, 2 (Box 12)
    - Additional 21, 3 (Box 12)
  - Audiovisual materials, Series IV
    - "Marilynne Robinson Interview" (work print: rough cut), undated; 1; 01:20:14 (Box 13, Item barcode 39002104612644)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Restricted fragile papers
    - Electronic media (Box 14)
      Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Restricted papers (Box 17)
    These materials are restricted until the death of Marilynne Robinson or January 1, 2050, whichever comes first. For further information consult the appropriate curator.